

(+1) 847-641-0586 <u>kaiyuhou2022@u.northwestern.edu</u> <u>www.kyhou.com</u> 1111 Church St. Apt. 605 Evanston, IL, 60201

I am currently a 4th year Ph.D. candidate in the Computer Science Department at Northwestern University, advised by Prof. Yan Chen. I have a broad interest in various aspects of cloud networks and network protocols. My current research focuses on network optimization of microservices/serverless based cloud. I am also working for introducing formal methods into network protocol verification.

Education

• Ph.D. Student in Computer Science Northwestern University

2017 - (2022)

Evanston, IL

- Advisor: Prof. Yan Chen

- Area: Networked System, Cloud Networking, Network Protocols

- GPA: 3.97/4.00

• Master's in Computer Science

2014 - 2017

Shaanxi, China

Xi'an Jiaotong University
- Advisor: Prof. Chengchen Hu

- Area: Software Defined Networking (SDN)

- Rank: 1st/89 GPA: 3.81/4.00 Average: 91.7

• B.E. in Software Engineering

2010 – 2014 Shaanxi, China

Xi'an Jiaotong University
- Rank: 1st/78 GPA: 3.94/4.00 Average: 92.4 (in Junior and Senior years)

- Thesis: Unsupervised Feature Selection Algorithm

Work Experiences

• SRI International Menlo Park, CA

Research Intern, at Computer Science Laboratory

Jun. 2020 - Sep. 2020

- Advisor: Dr. <u>Vinod Yegneswaran</u>
- Designed and implemented an enterprise-wide radio situational awareness system
- Passively collected radio traffics, including Wi-Fi and Bluetooth, analyzed by deep learning

Research: Cloud Networks & SDN

Network Optimizing for Microservices/Serverless Cloud (work in progress)

2020 - Present

- Microservices/serverless architectures bring flexibility but introduce network communication delay
- Designed systematic metrics to provide a benchmark for the microservices network performance
- Integrated QUIC into OpenFaaS/Kubernetes to improve serverless network performance

1

• Generic Security Policy Enforcement System for SDN-based Cloud

2017 - 2018

- Designed a **policy language** for resource protection and management of SDN-based Cloud
- Implemented in the OpenDaylight controller, and deployed on OpenStack

Publication: [IWQoS'18] Lightweight Resource Protection and Management System for SDN-based Cloud

• Routing Policy for Solving Reactive Model Overhead of SDN

2016 - 2017

- Proposed a routing policy to reduce the SDN control channel bandwidth consumption up to 80%
- Implemented in the Floodlight controller under the OpenFlow protocol with Open vSwitch
- Deployed on the ONetSwitch, an OpenFlow/P4 white-box switch with Xilinx FPGA

Publication: [ICNP'17] SoftRing: Taming the Reactive Model for Software Defined Networks

Research: Formal Methods for Network Protocols

• Formal Verification and Vulnerability Detection of LTE/5G Protocols

2019 - 2020

- Used **TLA+** to formally specify the emergency call systems in **4G/5G** cellular network protocols
- Built a **complete cellular network testbed** (USRP, OpenAirInterface) for real-world verification
- Discovered serious availability and security issues in real-world, acknowledged by major carriers

Publication: [Under Review] Discovering Emergency Call Pitfalls for Cellular Networks with Formal Methods

• Formal Secure Configuration Search for Network Protocols

2020 - 2021

- Traditionally, researchers use secure properties to verify a protocol is safe or find counterexamples
- We convert this decision problem into a search problem. Given the model and the properties, we aim to search the boundaries of the configuration space where the system is always secure and reliable
- We employ inductive generalization and improved IC3 algorithm to determine the space

Publication: [Sigcomm'20 Poster] Network Protocol Safe Configuration Search in One Shot

Publication List

• Property Guided Secure Configuration Space Search

You Li*, **Kaiyu Hou***, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou (*equal contribution) Under Review

• Discovering Emergency Call Pitfalls for Cellular Networks with Formal Methods

Kaiyu Hou*, You Li*, Yinbo Yu, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou (*equal contribution) Under Review

Network Protocol Safe Configuration Search in One Shot

You Li*, **Kaiyu Hou***, Hai Zhou, Yan Chen (*equal contribution)

ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication, Poster, 2020 (SIGCOMM'20)

• State of the Art and Research Challenges in the Security Technologies of Network Function Virtualization Xiaochun Wu, Kaiyu Hou, Xue Leng, Xing Li, Yinbo Yu, Bo Wu, Yan Chen IEEE Internet Computing, 2020

- *CellScope: Automatically Specifying and Verifying Cellular Network Protocols* Yinbo Yu, You Li, **Kaiyu Hou**, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou, Jianfeng Yang ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication, Poster, 2019 (SIGCOMM'19)
- A Lightweight Policy Enforcement System for Resource Protection and Management in the SDN-based Cloud Xue Leng, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Kai Bu, Libin Song, You Li Computer Networks, Elsevier, 2019
- COIN: A fast packet inspection method over compressed traffic
 Xiuwen Sun, Hao Li, Dan Zhao, Xingxing Lu, Kaiyu Hou, Chengchen Hu
 Journal of Network and Computer Applications, Elsevier, 2019
- SDNKeeper: Lightweight Resource Protection and Management System for SDN-based Cloud Xue Leng, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Kai Bu, Libin Song IEEE/ACM 26th International Symposium on Quality of Service, 2018 (IWQoS'18)
- SoftRing: Taming the Reactive Model for Software Defined Networks

 Chengchen Hu, Kaiyu Hou (1st student author), Hao Li, Ruilong Wang, Peng Zheng, Peng Zhang,
 Huanzhao Wang

 IEEE 25th International Conference on Network Protocols, 2017 (ICNP'17)
- Towards A Fast Packet Inspection over Compressed HTTP Traffic
 Xiuwen Sun, Kaiyu Hou, Hao Li, Chengchen Hu
 IEEE/ACM 25th International Symposium on Quality of Service, 2017 (IWQoS'16)

Teaching Experiences

CS 214: Data Structure and Data Man Teaching Assistant, Northwestern Univ		Winter, 2021
CS 214: Data Structure and Data Man Teaching Assistant, Northwestern Univ	•	Fall, 2020
CS 212, Mathematical Foundations of Teaching Assistant, Northwestern Univ.	•	Spring, 2020
• CS 340, Introduction to Networking (Teaching Assistant, Northwestern Univ	,	Winter, 2020
CS 214, Data Structure and Data Mana Teaching Assistant, Northwestern Univ	· ·	Fall, 2019
• EECS 343, Operating Systems Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	versity	Spring, 2019
• EECS 340, Introduction to Networkin Assistant Lecturer, Northwestern Univ	<u> </u>	Winter, 2019
• EECS 340, Introduction to Networkin	g	Fall, 2018

Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	
IT 458, Information Security and Assurance	Winter, 2018
Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	
 Computer Programming (C++) for CS Honored Class Teaching Assistant, Xi'an Jiaotong University 	Fall, 2016
Professional Services	
• Sub-reviewer of ACM CCS (2018, 2019)	
• Sub-reviewer of IEEE ICDCS (2018)	
 Reviewer of IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (ToN) 	
Awards	
Bronze Medal, ACM-ICPC Asia Regional Contest	2012, 2013, 2014
• Silver Medal, ACM-ICPC China Province Contest, Chengdu	2012, 2013
• Meritorious Winner, Mathematical Contest in Modeling (MCM)	2013
<u>Honor</u>	
• Best Teaching Assistant Award (<i>Peter and Adrienne Barris</i> Outstanding TA) <i>Northwestern University</i>	2020
• Outstanding Graduate (Cadre) Award Xi'an Jiaotong University	2017
• Excellent Postgraduate Student Leader Award (each year) Xi'an Jiaotong University	2015, 2016
• Outstanding Graduate Award Xi'an Jiaotong University	2014
• Excellent Student Model Nomination (16/13000) Xi'an Jiaotong University	2013
• Google Excellence Scholarship Awarded to 3 students from each of 20 top Chinese universities	2013
• Excellent Student Award (each year) Xi'an Jiaotong University	2011, 2012, 2013
Social Activities	
• Student President of the Computer Science Dept., (Class 2017) <i>Xi'an Jiaotong University</i>	2014 - 2017

•	Student Councilor , the Student Congress of ChungYing College <i>Xi'an Jiaotong University</i>	2013 - 2014
•	Chair, the ACM-ICPC Club Xi'an Jiaotong University	2012 - 2013
•	Science and Education Minister of the Student Union Xi'an Jiaotong University	2011-2012
•	Co-Founder & the 2 nd Store Manager of Bingo Cafe ChungYing College, Xi'an Jiaotong University	2010-2013

Skills

- TCP/IP Protocols, 3GPP Cellular Network Protocols (NAS layer), 802.11 Protocols, QUIC Protocol
- Serverless Platforms, Microservices Networks, Cloud Networks, SDN
- Formal Methods for Network Protocols, TLA+, IC3, NuSMV
- Python, Go-lang